Preston L. Pope Papers 1987.0029
Archives and Special Collections at the Thomas J. Dodd Research Center, University of Connecticut Library
Preston L. Pope Papers
1970-1981
Archives and Special Collections at the Thomas J. Dodd Research Center, University of Connecticut Library
1987.0029
0.25 Linear Feet
Materials related to Preston L. Pope's service, from 1978 to 1981, as Grand Master of the Prince Hall Grand Lodge, Free and Accepted Masons of Connecticut.
Access
The collection is open and available for research.
Provenance and Acquisition
The papers were donated by Preston L. Pope in June 1987.
Biography
Preston L. Pope was born on January 25, 1920, in Yantley, Alabama, the son of James Hanover Pope and Viver Brown Pope, and moved with his family at a young age to Philadelphia, Pennsylvania. He served in the United States Army during World War II. After the war, he moved to Connecticut and married to Doris Stewart. He and his wife had two children, Preston Jr. and Patricia, and resided in Windsor, Connecticut.
Mr. Pope is known as the first African-American bus driver in Hartford, Connecticut, for the Connecticut Company. In his work as a printer he was employed by the State of Connecticut Corrections Institute as the supervisor of printing for the Somers State Prison. He retired in 1982.
Mr. Pope was made a member of Excelsior Lodge #3, Free and Accepted Masons, Prince Hall Affiliation, on November 1, 1947, and rose to the rank of 33rd degree. In 1978 he was elected to the office of Most Worshipful Grand Master of the Jurisdiction of Connecticut of the Prince Hall Grand Lodge, and served until October 1981. He founded and organized the Hartford Consistory, #80, in Hartford, Connecticut, and served as Grand High Priest of Holy Royal Arch Masons of Connecticut and as Past Eminent Grand Commander of Knights Templar of the Territory of Connecticut.
A video commemorating Mr. Pope's life is available on YouTube.
Preston L. Pope died on April 30, 2012.
Scope and Content Note
The Papers consist of publications, correspondence, and news articles gathered by Preston L. Pope> when he served as Grand Master of the Prince Hall Grand Lodge, Free and Accepted Masons of Connecticut.
Societies; Correspondence; Newspapers; Publications (documents); Labor unions; Administrative records; African Americans; Freemasons. Prince Hall Grand Lodge of Connecticut; Royal Arch Masons; Pope, Preston L.
- Series I: Papers, 1970-1981
  - Annual Address by Preston L. Pope to the Prince Hall Grand Lodge, Free and Accepted Masons of Connecticut, 1979 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Annual Address by Preston L. Pope to the Prince Hall Grand Lodge, Free and Accepted Masons of Connecticut, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Annual Address by Preston L. Pope to the Prince Hall Grand Lodge, Free and Accepted Masons of Connecticut, 1981 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Souvenir booklets of the Prince Hall Grand Chapter Holy Royal Arch Masons, State of Connecticut, Annual Convocations and Testimonial Banquet, 1970, 1972, 1973 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence from Preston L. Pope to Prince Hall Grand Lodge members, 1978-1979 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - News articles about issues involving the Prince Hall Grand Lodge, 1979-1981 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Roster of Prince Hall Grand Lodge masters, 1981 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Address of the Grand Master of the Most Worshipful Grand Lodge, Ancient Free and Accepted Masons in Connecticut, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Connecticut Squares & Compasses a publication of the Grand Lodge, Ancient Free and Accepted Masons of Connecticut, 1981 October-December (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Inner City Bicentennial Booklet, 1776-1976, by John E. Rogers, described as "a joint effort of the Connecticut State Board of Education and the Afro-American History Section of Black Studies of the University of Hartford and the Greater Hartford Community College, 1975 (Box 1, Folder 10)